Finding Aid for Kent Terwilliger papers, 1956-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kent Terwilliger papers 1956-1989
Terwilliger, Kent, 1924-1989.
8 linear feet
90206 Aa 2
University of Michigan professor of physics, 1952-1989; specialist in high-energy particle physics; department of physics associate chairman for research, 1985-1989.Papers relating to his research, teaching and administrative activities; include experiment files, topical files, class files and some physics department materials; also some materials on the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project and the Michigan Superconducting Super Collider Commission; also includes some papers of Alan Krisch.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Doris H. Terwilliger (Donor No. 7723 ) in August 1989.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Kent M. Terwilliger was born June 17, 1924 in San Jose, California. He received his B.S. in physics from the California Institute of Technology in 1949, and his Ph.D. in physics from the University of California, Berkeley in 1952. He joined the University of Michigan Physics Department as an instructor in 1952, and became assistant professor in 1956, associate professor in 1960, and full professor in 1965. Professor Terwilliger specialized in high-energy particle physics, and specifically in the study of acceleration of polarized proton beams, a form of research which analyzes proton behavior during violent collisions.
In the 1950s, Professor Terwilliger was involved with the Midwest Universities Research Association (MURA), working with Lawrence Jones on accelerator design. They developed a system using the beam stacking procedure and quadrupole lenses which provided aid for colliding beam experiments requiring a small target size. This system was incorporated into the design of the CERN Intersecting Storage Rings.
In the early 1960s, Terwilliger did work in the area of particle detection. While the bubble chamber (developed in the 1950s by Donald Glaser) was the most well-known of the University of Michigan's contributions to the methods of particle detection, problems with the automated scanning required by the bubble chamber led to exploration of alternative particle detectors. The initiation of spark chamber work at Michigan by Terwilliger and Don Meyer was one such exploration. During the 1960s, Terwilliger was involved in a series of experiments using the spark chamber: an experiment to study a new particle; an elastic -p scattering experiment at the Argonne National Laboratory Zero Gradient Synchrotron (ZGS); an experiment to study the meson; and experiments studying backward inelastic and elastic -p scattering.
During the 1970s and 1980s, Terwilliger worked with Professor Alan Krisch's research group, doing polarized proton-proton scattering at the ZGS, and studying the dependence of the differential and total cross sections on the transverse spin state of the beam and target particles. In 1978, Krisch's group instigated a study for the conversion of the Brookhaven National Laboratory Alternating Gradient Synchrotron (AGS) to polarized proton acceleration, since shutdown of the ZGS in October 1979 would effectively end their work at the Argonne National Laboratory. From 1980 to 1984 Krisch and Terwilliger spent much time assisting the BNL in developing polarized proton acceleration capability at the AGS. Michigan's specific responsibilities were for development and production of 12 pulsed quadrupoles and for internal and high energy polarimeters. Terwilliger also continued to collaborate with Krisch in studying spin dependences in high energy large transverse momentum proton-proton elastic scattering.
During the late 1980s, a major concern of Krisch's group was that a successful future of polarized beams at much higher energies would require new methods of avoiding depolarizing resonances. The Russian "Siberian Snake" scheme was seen as a possible solution, and as of May 1988 an experimental test was planned at the Indiana University Cyclotron Facility.
Professor Terwilliger served on a number of national high energy physics committees and panels during his career. In 1964 he received both a Guggenheim Fellowship and a CERN visiting scientist fellowship to study in Geneva, Switzerland. In 1972 he again received a CERN visiting scientist fellowship. Terwilliger also served on numerous University of Michigan committees, including the Physics Department Executive Committee and the 1982-1983 Review Committee for the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project Grant Program. From 1985 to 1989, Terwilliger served as the Physics Department Associate Chairman for Research.
The collection is divided into two series: Research and Personal Materials and Teaching and Administrative Materials. Terwilliger's curriculum vita (including a list of publications and classes taught) and yearly letters summarizing his research activities are located in the first folder of Box 1.
Subjects:
Argonne National Laboratory.; Brookhaven National Laboratory.; European Council for Nuclear Research.; Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project.; Michigan. Superconducting Super Collider Commission.; Particles (Nuclear physics); Physics.; Terwilliger, Kent, 1924-1989.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Scientific equipment.
Contributors:
Krisch, A. D.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Research and Personal Materials
  The Research and Personal Materials series contains experiment files, topical files relating to research, articles and lectures, correspondence and some of Terwilliger's own student notes. The experiment files and topical files are closely related, and together document the entire span of Terwilliger's research career, although materials from the 1950s are somewhat sparse. The experiment files have been placed in a rough chronological order, and the topical files in alphabetical order. Terwilliger's folder titles have been retained, with experiment titles added when possible. The files themselves include handwritten notes, charts, graphs, draft papers and occasionally photographs.
  Printed articles and lectures may be found with the experiments to which they relate, as well as in the "articles and lectures" folders. As Alan Krisch and Terwilliger worked closely together, some Krisch materials are also scattered through the collection. The six folders of correspondence are largely research-related, and the student notes are believed to be Terwilliger's from his undergraduate or graduate student days, but they are unidentified and undated.
  - Curriculum vita and yearly research summaries (Box 1)
  - Experiment Files
    - π-+p→Y° + K°, Experiment and Calculations 1960-1963
      - General (Box 1)
      - Photographs (Box 1)
    - Beam Setup and Y Experiment 1961 (Box 1)
    - π++D p+p Experiment 1963 (Box 1)
    - π?+p Elastic Scattering, π++D→p+p, Theory and Experiment Results 1963-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Research Notebooks
      - I. September-November, 1964 CERN (Box 1)
      - II. December 1964-March 1965 CERN (Box 1)
      - III. April 1965-July 1965 CERN (Box 1)
      - IV. September 1965-August 1966 (Box 1)
      - V. August 1966-August 1969 (Box 1)
      - VI. August 1969 (Box 1)
    - π-p Backward Elastic and Inelastic Scattering at 2.15 GeV/c (E-126)
      - General (Box 1)
      - Alignment December 1966-January 1967 (Box 1)
      - #1 Tuning, Test Data January 1967 (Box 1)
      - #2 Tuning, Test Data January 1967 (Box 1)
      - #3 Data February 1967 (Box 1)
      - #4 Data March 1967 (Box 1)
      - N* Analysis 1967 (Box 1)
      - N* Backward Production (E-126) 1967-1969 (Box 1)
      - N* (E-126) 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Rho Experiment (E-40, ZGS) 1966-1970 (Box 1)
    - Rho Experiment (E-40, ZGS) 1966-1971 (Box 2)
    - National Accelerator Laboratory Experiment E-6 (200 GeV Proton Elastic Scattering) 1970-1973, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Distribution in Transverse Momentum of 5 GeV/c Secondaries Produced at 53 GeV in the Center of Mass 1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - π-p Backward Experiment 1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Rho Production and Decay in the Reaction π-p→ π? π° p at 5 GeV/c 1973 (Box 2)
    - Simultaneous Measurement of 2 and 3 Spins in p-p Elastic Scattering at 6 GeV/c 1974 and earlier (Box 2)
    - Total Cross Section 1975 (Box 2)
    - Measurement of Proton-Proton Elastic Scattering at 6 GeV/c in Polarized Initial and Final Spin States 1975-1978, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 3 Spin Figures 1977 (Box 2)
    - Neutron Detector (Spin-Spin Forces in 6 GeV/c Neutron-Proton Elastic Scattering) 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - Energy Dependence of Spin-Spin Effects in p-p Elastic Scattering at 90 cm 1975-1981 (Box 3)
    - 11.75 GeV/c 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    - Inclusive Experiment p+p 1977-1981 (Box 3)
    - 6 GeV/c 1978-1982 (Box 3)
    - Depolarizing Resonances/Siberian Snake Experiment 1978-1988 (Box 3)
    - Measurement of Spin Effects in p-p Elastic Scattering Using the Polarised Beam at the AGS 1988 (Box 3)
    - NEPTUN-A Experiment (USA/USSR) 1988, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Research Topical Files
    - Accelerator Calculations 1956-1960 (Box 3)
    - Accelerator Talk 1958-1971, undated (Box 3)
    - Accelerator Technology, Formulas and References undated (Box 3)
    - Argonne Accelerator (ZGS) Users Group 1959-1962 (Box 3)
    - Argonne Accelerator (ZGS) Users Group 1963-1977 (Box 3)
    - Automatic Scan 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - Beam Design Program (Fortran) 1961-1964 (Box 3)
    - Beam Design 1958-1988, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - CERN Intersecting Storage Rings, Terwilliger Scheme 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - CERN Physics Conference 1962 (Box 4)
    - Conferences 1977-1979 (Box 4)
    - DUBNA Conference 1964 (Box 4)
    - Electric Camera 1960 (Box 4)
    - High Energy Physics Conference 1980 (Box 4)
    - High Energy Physics Lectures (Box 4)
    - High Energy Spin Symposium 1982 (Box 4)
    - High Energy Spin Symposium 1988 (Box 4)
    - Microwave Spark Counters 1959-1960 (Box 4)
    - p+p General Topic, Electronics Calculations 1976-1982 (Box 4)
    - p-p Kinematics (Box 4)
    - Physics Talk 1964-1971, undated (Box 4)
    - Polarimeter 1981 (Box 4)
    - Polarization Conference, High P Elastic Scattering 1978 (Box 4)
    - Proposed Experiment Calculations 1961-1962 (Box 4)
    - Radio Frequency Quadrupole 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Reflection Program, Three Body Decay 1967 (Box 4)
    - Technical Advisory Panel on Polarization 1975 (Box 4)
    - ZGS Early Experiments Talk 1982 (Box 4)
  - Articles and Lectures
    - 1970-1985, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1985-1988 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1954-1988, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Student Notes
    - Quantum Mechanics (Box 5)
    - Advanced Quantum Mechanics-Case (Box 5)
    - Nuclear Physics (Box 5)
    - Statistical Mechanics (Box 5)
    - Physics 224 (Box 5)
    - Physics and Math Summaries (Box 5)
- Teaching and Administrative Materials
  The Teaching and Administrative Materials series includes University of Michigan class files, topical files related to teaching and University of Michigan administrative files.
  - Class Files
    Class files have been arranged numerically and identified by title when possible. Much material in these files is undated, but they appear to cover Terwilliger's entire teaching career, from about 1956 to 1989. The class files contain handwritten lecture notes, exam copies and problem sets and solutions.
    - Physics 45 (Physics 25) Lecture Notes (Box 5)
    - Physics 46 (Physics 26) Lecture Notes (Box 5)
    - Physics 126 (Box 5)
    - Physics 125 and Physics 140, 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Physics 125 and Physics 140, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Physics 140, Special Relativity (Box 6)
    - Physics 140 Honors (Box 6)
    - Physics 190 (Box 6)
    - Physics 191 Lab, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Physics 196 (Box 6)
    - Physics 240 K (Box 6)
    - Physics 240, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Honors College 252, Conceptions in 20th Century Physics (Box 6)
    - Physics 307 (Box 6)
    - Physics 401, Mechanics (Box 6)
    - Physics 402, Light (Box 6)
    - Physics 405, Electricity and Magnetism, 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Physics 405, Electricity and Magnetism, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Physics 406, Statistical and Thermal Physics, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Physics 453, Atomic Physics I (Box 7)
    - Physics 457, Nuclear Physics (Box 7)
    - Physics 459, Nuclear Lab (Box 7)
    - Physics 461, Atomic Physics Lab (Box 7)
    - Physics 468, Elementary Particles (Box 7)
    - Physics 517, Graduate Physics Laboratory (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Syllabi/Exams (Physics 105, 107, 197, 198, 511) (Box 7)
  - Teaching Topical Files
    - Accelerators (Box 7)
    - Dispersion Theory (Box 7)
    - Field Theory, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Formulas and References (Box 7)
    - High Energy Physics (Box 7)
    - High Energy Physics Regge Theory (Box 7)
    - Labs (Box 7)
    - Notes (Box 7)
    - Relativity (Box 7)
    - Weak Interactions (Box 7)
  - Administrative Files
    The administrative files provide general information about the programs and policies of the Physics Department, although Terwilliger's position as Associate Chairman for Research is not specifically documented. Memos, correspondence and some committee minutes are included. Materials relating to Terwilliger's involvement with the Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project and the Michigan Superconducting Super Collider Task Force are also included. The bulk of the administrative materials date from the 1980s.
    - Physics Department
      - Executive Committee 1964-1987 (Box 8)
      - Executive Committee 1987-1989, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Five Year Plan 1985 (Box 8)
      - General 1958-1984, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - General 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - High Energy Physics Search (Box 8)
      - Committee 1981-1985 (Box 8)
      - Newsletter 1983-1987 (Box 8)
      - Review Committee 1972-1982, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Michigan Memorial Phoenix Project
      - Faculty Executive Committee (Box 8)
      - Minutes 1980-1983 (Box 8)
      - Review Committee 1983 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Superconducting Super Collider Task Force 1987-1988 (Box 8)